ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 F
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU Motion Picture Films
1936-1985
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA)
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union (ACTWU)
5619 F
28.11 cubic feet
28 linear ft.
Motion picture films.
7544308
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 12, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, May 04, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619: ACWA Records 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio-Visual Materials
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union.; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America.
7544308
- Adlai Stevenson/ACWA Rally, 1956 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  [74] -- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; 1956; 16mm; good - Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English --Adlai Stevenson Presidential Campaign, Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA), 1956 Presidential campaign, political action. The film is a speech by Adlai Stevenson, Democratic Candidate for President in 1956. The speech is given at a rally in New York City held by the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. It is an energizing speech where he claims that the US must be the "moral leader of free people everywhere." Adlai Stevenson Democratic Presidential Candidate in 1956, Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 15 min. long. Film # 38., two prints; second print is in good condition -- 775 feet of film
- Union with a heart (Box 2)
- Union and Community, 1950 (Box 3)
  [73] -- United States Army; 1950; 16mm; good condition; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Community involvement, Community service; community action through unions; Chester, PA This is a documentary narrated by Ed Orsel, a worker at the locomotive plant in Chester, PA. The narrator tells the story of how he became involved in community organizing and public service through the involvement in his union and its members. Orsel becomes a community activist in many respects and assumes the responsibility of helping others in need. The main crisis in the film is when a boy gets hit by a car while crossing the street. Orsel and other union members start a public safety campaign and petition the citizens to sign up. They presented this petition and a proposal for more street signs, stop lights, police and crossing guards, to the city council. The proposal passes and the streets are made safer. This shows the potential of community organizing and union's responsibility to mobilize its members around giving back to the community. Chester, Pennsylvania; property of Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America Film Division. 15 min. long. -- 680 feet of film
- For the Record (Box 4)
  [75] -- Julian Hoffman; Thomas Brando - Public Affairs Film Production; 16mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Post WW II strikes; plant shutdowns; layoffs. The film is about the struggles endured by strikers in the mid-late 1940's. The film describes the hardships of striking workers in these years and what kind of opposition and support they faced. It tells about plant shutdowns and employee layoffs as well as local stores and businesses that supported union labor. The end of the film stresses that union members must stay strong and recognize the need to organize so union's power increases. For the Record, 18 min. long. -- 800 feet of film
- Sit Down!, 1937 (Box 5)
  [44] - "Spanish Version"; American Federation of Hosiery Workers, Hosiery Styles for 1937; Education Department of American Federation of Hosiery Workers; 16 mm; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Hosiery Sit Down Strikes of 1937, Philadelphia Hosiery Workers This is a silent film about the Hosier Workers of Philadelphia in 1937. They joined together and staged massive Sit Down strikes throughout the city of Philadelphia. The film shows how union members joined together in surviving the strike by cooking meals for each other and supporting one another. The employers started negotiating after a while, and soon the unions won. The sit down strikes of 1937 were successful union activities. Sit Down, American Federation of Hosiery Workers; 16 min. long --- 600 feet of film
- Union and Community, 1950 (Box 6)
  [73] - United States Army 1950; 16mm; good condition; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Community involvement, Community service; community action through unions; Chester, PA This is a documentary narrated by Ed Orsel, a worker at the locomotive plant in Chester, PA. The narrator tells the story of how he became involved in community organizing and public service through the involvement in his union and its members. Orsel becomes a community activist in many respects and assumes the responsibility of helping others in need. The main crisis in the film is when a boy gets hit by a car while crossing the street. Orsel and other union members start a public safety campaign and petition the citizens to sign up. They presented this petition and a proposal for more street signs, stop lights, police and crossing guards, to the city council. The proposal passes and the streets are made safer. This shows the potential of community organizing and union's responsibility to mobilize its members around giving back to the community. Chester, Pennsylvania; property of Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America Film Division. 15 min. long. -- 700 feet of film
- Millions of Us (Box 7)
  [76] - American Labor Films; 16mm; good, yet missing opening frames; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Hopelessness and unemployment, working class power; organizing. The film is the story of a homeless, unemployed gentleman who has trouble finding work in a society that is geared for the wealthy and middle class. He finds work at a plant that is on strike and is stopped at the door by the striking workers for being a "scab". One of the workers explains the cause of the strike and need for working people, like himself, to rise up and show their power against management. He stresses the need to organize and not be divided. The main character then understands the cause and walked the strike line with the workers. Title frames not present, no lead, 20 min. long. -- 650 feet of film
- Poverty in the Valley of Plenty (Box 8)
  [72] - AFL; 16mm; good (both prints); Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; California corporate farmworkers, farmworkers strike and DiGiorgio Corporation; Taft-Hartley Act; illegal immigrants. The film is the story of California Farmworkers who are denied decent wages and living conditions under employment with the DiGiorgio Corporation. The workers are forced to work long shifts under bad conditions and without federally mandated or company benefits of any kind. The workers decide to organize under the AFL and strike the employer. In response, DiGiorgio brings in "wetbacks", or illegal immigrants from Mexico to replace those workers on strike. The strike is plagued with violence and unrest. The film also makes the point that the Taft-Hartley Act of 1947 does nothing to help farmworkers and purposely keeps them out of NLRA jurisdiction. Poverty in the Valley of Plenty, 22 min. long. -- 800 feet of film
- The Fourth Battle, 1958 (Box 9)
  [71] - Nicholas Read; Washington Video Production; c. 1957-58; 16mm; good condition; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Strike of O'Sullivan Rubber Corporation Strike at Winchester, Virginia by Local 511 of the United Rubber Workers in 1956 and 1957, decertification The film tells the story of the United Rubber Workers Local 511 and their strike of the O'Sullivan Rubber Corporation in Winchester, Virginia. There were three major battles fought in Winchester in both the Revolutionary and Civil Wars and this film tells the story of the "Fourth Battle". After being on strike for 17 months, the strikebreakers voted to de-certify Local 511 and strand the striking workers on the picket lines without a job or a union. The film is a good documentary of the costs and work that go into a strike and the vulnerability of strikers to both their employer, and other workers who disagree with the cause. The Fourth Battle, United Rubber Workers of America. 16 min. long. -- 700 feet of film
- "Bizarre footage from the 1940s (Box 10)
  [57] - 1940s; 16 mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Vermont state CIO marching in a parade with High School graduates. "Bizarre footage from the 1940's" -- 600 feet of film
- The Shop Steward (Box 11)
  [85] - Morton Parker; National Film Board of Canada - Guy Grover; 16 mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Shop Steward training, Canada, Steelworkers. This film is the story about a worker in a Canadian steelworker plant. The worker is elected to be shop steward and quickly learns the responsibilities of the job. The film shows how the shop steward got someone's job back after they were fired for unjust reasons. The film stresses the importance of a good shop steward and the work that goes into being one. The Shop Steward, Kodak Safety Film, 22 min. long. -- 1000 feet of film
- AFL-CIO Americans at Work (Box 12)
  [60] - Nor wood Studios, Washington D.C. 16 mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; textiles; health and safety. This film is about the industry that has developed around synthetic fiber as opposed to natural fibers such as cotton, wool and silk. The film talks about the process of creating synthetic fiber from wood and the hazards and technology associated with it. The film emphasizes that a well educated union membership along with an "enlightened management" will lead to minimal health and safety accidents. Americans at Work; Kodak Safety Film; 13 min. long. -- 600 feet of film
- All in Favor (Box 13)
  [90] - Sheila Page and Susan Zig Ellen Wernick - Coalition of Labor Union Women; 16mm; good; Color; On Reel; Positive; English; Coalition of Labor Union Women, Women in the labor movement. This film is about women in the labor movement. It is a series of interviews with labor women ranging from President of a local union to staff organizers who have moved their way off the shop floor and into the union office. It stresses the need to organize unorganized women in the work force. It also stresses the need for women to assume responsibility for their working conditions and help mobilize their co-workers and get involved in politics. The film also speaks about the need to address women's issues through union activity. There is a more detailed description in the shipping container. All in Favor, 17 min. long. --- 600 feet of film
- Hubert H. Humphrey, 1977 (Box 14)
  [48] - Speech at 1977 AFL-CIO Convention; Al Barked; Maurer, Fleisher, Zon and Anderson, Inc.; 1977; 16 mm; good; Color; On Reel; Positive; English; Hubert H. Humphrey, 1977 AFL-CIO Convention, Legislation, This is a speech given by Hubert H. Humphrey in one of his last public appearances. He calls for the labor movement to examine its roots and rekindle the flame of years past. He cites the improvements unions have won in people's lives, i.e. Medicare, pensions, eta He pushes the "Humphrey-Hawkins Bill", which holds government responsible for enacting legislation for the purpose of economic advancement through full employment. He urges the union members to never give up their battle and take the lead as a strengthening economic and social movement to confront the problem of unemployment and push government toward progressive legislation. Hubert H. Humphrey; 20 min. long. Kodak Safety Film; good condition -- 800 feet of film
- Textile Workers Panel Discussion (Box 15)
  [101] - 1955; 16mm; good, both prints; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Panel Discussion, Textile Workers Union of America, New England Textile Mills, negotiations. The film is a panel discussion by various local leaders of the Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA) from the New England Area. They talk about efficiency and the high profits of New England textile mills and their ability to provide a decent living wage to workers. The panel is upset over negotiations at one of the mills where the employer is offering virtually nothing and the employees plan to strike. Textile Workers Panel Discussion, 16 min. long. -- 600 feet of film
- Local 100 (Box 16)
  [65] - Bernard Devlin; James Beveridge; 16 mm; fair, short lead, a little choppy at the beginning, no title frames; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Canadian trade unions, organizing. This is a film about a factory in Canada that organized when one of the workers was fired unjustly. It is narrated by the union organizer that was sent in by the Local 100 to organize the workers there who were looking for representation. The film follows the progression of the campaign up until the first contract is agreed upon. Local 100, 31 min. long, Kodak Safety film, no title frames present -- 1000 feet of film
- Hickson (Box 17)
  [20] -- 400 feet of film
- 1938 Atlantic City Convention (Box 18)
  [5a] - AQUA 1938; 16 mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Atlantic City, New Jersey, Sidney Hillman. This is a series of reels from the ACWA Convention (1938). 1) (film 5A) This film opens with the beginning of the convention. Delegates are seen strolling along the boardwalk and getting to know one another. The second half of this film shows delegates frolicking in a park, possibly rehearsing skits.
- Camp Arcola, 1941 (Box 19)
  [10] -- 275 feet of film
- Clothing workers at work (Box 20)
  [8] -- 350 feet of film
- Look for the Union label (Box 21)
  -- 300 feet of film
- Mass meeting Cincinnati, 1937 (Box 22)
  [14] -- 350 feet of film
- Union mades (Box 23)
  [11] -- 450 feet of film
- Local 717 ACWA (Box 24)
  [187] -- Chambersburg, Pa. Family picnic 7" reel -- 400 feet of film
- To Promote the General Welfare (Box 25)
  [36] - AQUA; 16 mm; good; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Harry Truman accepts the Sidney Hillman Award This film is made by the ACWA and shows the acceptance speech made by Harry Truman upon receiving the 5th Annual Sidney Hillman Award for public service and social welfare. Truman speaks about the need to have new ideas to fix things in our country, we have to be innovative and aim higher. He said we should all do this in the spirit of Sidney Hillman and his efforts to "promote the general welfare" To Promote the General Welfare, 12 min. long. Safety film -- 150 feet of film
- Stray lamb (Box 26)
  [25] -- 2 feet of film
- Amalgamated hosiery workers protest (Box 27)
  [39] -- 275 feet of film
- Outs from Union Label (Box 28)
  [17] -- 300 feet of film
- Some convention stuff with Hillman and LaGuardia (Box 29)
  [35] -- 350 feet of film
- Militia save (Box 30)
  [26] -- 325 feet of film
- To promote the general welfare, 1948 (Box 31)
  [6] - 200 feet of film
- One world or none (Box 32)
  [28] -- 350 feet of film
- Union and Community [needs repair, not working order), 1950 (Box 33)
  [73] - United States Army, 1950; 16mm; good condition; Black and White; On Reel; Positive; English; Community involvement, Community service; community action through unions; Chester, PA This is a documentary narrated by Ed Orsel, a worker at the locomotive plant in Chester, PA. The narrator tells the story of how he became involved in community organizing and public service through the involvement in his union and its members. Orsel becomes a community activist in many respects and assumes the responsibility of helping others in need. The main crisis in the film is when a boy gets hit by a car while crossing the street. Orsel and other union members start a public safety campaign and petition the citizens to sign up. They presented this petition and a proposal for more street signs, stop lights, police and crossing guards, to the city council. The proposal passes and the streets are made safer. This shows the potential of community organizing and union's responsibility to mobilize its members around giving back to the community. Chester, Pennsylvania; property of Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America Film Division. 15 min. long. -- 325 feet of film
- JFK and LBJ (roll #4); track JFK (200, 202) // TKG: ACTWU - 06708-Inheritance (Box 34)
  Track for Roll #3-N/A; Track for Roll #4-N/A; TRK; SYNC -- roll #4-225 feet of film; roll #3-75 feet of film
- 11th Biennial Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America Convention, 1936 -- Cleveland Convetion (Box 35)